Hello
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): everybody. I had an interesting discussion with Bronco Marchatic, who is a writer mostly on foreign policy for Jacobin magazine and in these times, other places, and is an astute observer in that area. So I wanted to get his assessment of the state of things among the Democratic candidates.
In the
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): realm of foreign policy and the conversation sort of diverged in a few places, but that's to be expected I Think Nonetheless you will find it quite interesting. So here we go All
right, hello Bronco Hi Michael Even
Speaker 2: though you just gave me
Speaker 3: a primer on how do you pronounce your last name? I'm gonna spare myself
and
Speaker 3: um
Speaker 4: quite all right
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): i'm uh i want to be the uh the share of the uh you know the the left-wing journalist scene so you know if i just get to know by my first
Speaker 6 (lower-pitched voice): name that's fine i
Speaker 7: respect that and actually it's a it's
Speaker 8 (lower-pitched voice): a good first name to go by with just the singular you know it has a little bit of mystique to it whereas i couldn't get away with going
by michael
Speaker 9: yeah yeah to sort of too many guys called Michael in the US you know I mean I'm lucky because back in in
Speaker 10: Serbia if I was still there Branko is not that uncommon a name so you know I get away with kind of being exotic when I'm in a
Speaker 11: English-speaking
Speaker 12: country yeah you know being named Michael it meant that growing up I was
Speaker 13 (lower-pitched voice): surrounded by about a thousand other Michaels and so that leads
Speaker 8 (lower-pitched voice): to a situation where you end up being called by your last
name.
Speaker 13 (lower-pitched voice): Oh, you know, so it's like, it's like a schoolyard thing where it's, you know, you call you, you get called Tracy, which is like, fine, I guess. But
once you
Speaker 13 (lower-pitched voice): reach it,
Speaker 14 (lower-pitched voice): when you're in school, that's, that can be a very wounding thing. Probably. I don't
Speaker 15: know why we're talking about this. But I mean,
kids will
Speaker 16 (lower-pitched voice): always find something to hit you with. I've,
Speaker 17 (lower-pitched voice): I've had many.
Speaker 17 (lower-pitched voice): uh, versions of, of all manner of kind of, kind of slurs right to my name. So, you know,
Speaker 18: yeah. All right. So let's move beyond that absolute nonsense and
Speaker 19 (lower-pitched voice): begin the discussion, uh, that I wanted to have with you, which is
about foreign
Speaker 19 (lower-pitched voice): policy and the, and the presidential candidates. I mean, you are, uh, you have, you've covered the foreign policy views of
Speaker 20 (lower-pitched voice): the candidates for different publications now for several years. Um, um,
Speaker 20 (lower-pitched voice): First
of
Speaker 13 (lower-pitched voice): all, I guess just by way of background, I was reading one of your In These Times articles and at the end you sort of like reference how bizarre, I guess, peers of yours found it that you studied US politics in New Zealand. What was the
Speaker 21 (lower-pitched voice): source of their confusion or why did they react that way and how would you address
that?
well I think
Speaker 22: for a lot of people they a lot of people don't
Speaker 14 (lower-pitched voice): happen to have a chance to meet a New Zealander and then also for a New Zealander to be interested in US politics and to be writing
Speaker 23 (lower-pitched voice): about it you know whether professionally or not I think it's kind of like a like a novelty for people
Speaker 10: it's very strange and and a lot of cases kind of inexplicable you know I mean I would say
that
For
Speaker 10: one, I think American citizens don't realize that the entire world follows US politics very closely, not just random New Zealanders, but, you know, all over the place, you know, whether it's, whether we're talking about Europe, Asia, wherever. You know, so I don't know if that's a thing that people realize yet, but it's,
Speaker 17 (lower-pitched voice): what happens in the US is of intense interest.
Speaker 17 (lower-pitched voice): People all over the world have very fierce debates about what's happening in the U.S. political system. In fact, I can tell you, I remember
Speaker 10: a time when I was taking the bus back from university in Auckland, New Zealand. I and a friend of mine,
Speaker 17 (lower-pitched voice): we overheard a guy at the back having a very spurted debate with someone about why Mitt Romney
Speaker 10: was the better candidate instead of Obama. So, you know, there's people, even though they're not based in the U.S., have very...
Speaker 10: Intense feelings about,
Speaker 14 (lower-pitched voice): you know, whether candidates or policies that are being pursued in the U.S. And except except
Speaker 24: that the New Zealand embassy in Washington or wherever it happens to be
Speaker 13 (lower-pitched voice): located, I don't think you'd hear a single discussion in the United States about who would be the better.
Speaker 13 (lower-pitched voice): Prime Minister of New Zealand. I think
it's
Speaker 25: safe to say that New Zealand and what goes on in New Zealand is probably not on the top of the priorities for most Americans. And, you know, I mean, nor
Speaker 17 (lower-pitched voice): should it be really, because what New Zealand does does not really affect the
Man 26: U.S. that much.
Speaker 25: Except for the fact
Speaker 16 (lower-pitched voice): that we do have a very powerful agricultural sector. And so that was actually when the TPP was being hammered out, there was a lot of...
Speaker 17 (lower-pitched voice): uh, anxiety among us policymakers because they were worried that, uh, well, you know, if we, if we now open, open up free trade with, uh, with New Zealand,
Speaker 10: then, you know, the dairy sector may steamroll ours. So, you know, on, on a few issues, there's some worry, but, uh, for
the
Speaker 14 (lower-pitched voice): most part, I don't think, uh, Americans should be too concerned about what happens in New Zealand.
Speaker 13 (lower-pitched voice): Um, it, it, it, it briefly burst onto at least pockets of,
uh,
Speaker 13 (lower-pitched voice): political consciousness.
Speaker 8 (lower-pitched voice): I remember in 2013 when the Snowden episode happened because New Zealand is a member of Five Eyes, you know, the intelligence sharing
Speaker 27 (lower-pitched voice): alliance. So, you know, but that's one of the very few instances in which it actually became a salient political issue. And even
Speaker 28: then it wasn't particularly widespread. No,
Speaker 29: no.
Speaker 10: And, you know, there's a little more now because I think our prime minister, our current prime minister, Jacinda Ardern, has sort of become
the
Speaker 16 (lower-pitched voice): Excuse me, the new
Speaker 17 (lower-pitched voice): Trudeau of, I guess, international politics. You know, Trudeau's star has kind of faded. Even before this latest blackface scandal
Speaker 30: happened, he kind of – people were increasingly
Speaker 16 (lower-pitched voice): kind of
–
Speaker 16 (lower-pitched voice): becoming smart to what a sham his his kind of branding and social media and Viral, you
Speaker 31 (lower-pitched voice): know moments all that stuff that people kind of cottoning on to the fact that it was a very thinly veiled kind of PR campaign to paper over some of his more
Speaker 31 (lower-pitched voice): you know, terrible policies. So now Jacinda Ardern has kind of become that figure for, you know, people around the world who can who want, especially in the US who wants to look to a a liberal leader somewhere in the world to kind of forget Trump and go, you know, oh, wouldn't it be nice if we had this,
Speaker 32: right? I believe she wrote an
op
Speaker 13 (lower-pitched voice): ed for the New York Times after the Christchurch.
Speaker 13 (lower-pitched voice): massacre
Speaker 27 (lower-pitched voice): and i can recall the response to that being like wistful longing for somebody like her to be in charge of sort of like emergency response were something of that sort to happen in the u.s
yeah yeah
Speaker 10: that sounds about right um but you know i would also i would also warn uh
Speaker 17 (lower-pitched voice): americans you know i'm not in any way saying our donors as bad as trudeau but uh you know also you know I have a little skepticism,
Speaker 17 (lower-pitched voice): is also a politician she's by no means perfect there's a lot of criticism from the left of her in New Zealand so
Speaker 16 (lower-pitched voice): you know just because you you might read and see a lot of things that look
Speaker 10: good there's always a little more to the story than you might assume
and she
Speaker 33: also gave birth while in office right which I know a lot of people found impressive
yes
Speaker 34: yes she did she I think she became pregnant
Speaker 34: Very soon after she won the election and yeah, she gave birth, which is obviously an incredibly difficult thing to do
Speaker 17 (lower-pitched voice): anyway, let alone when you're running a country, you know, unsurprisingly, or maybe surprisingly to some people, the country did not fall apart while she was, you know, off giving birth and our deputy prime minister ran the country. It was totally fine.
Speaker 17 (lower-pitched voice): nothing terrible happened um so you know hopefully if that if that's a sort of example for the rest of the world to take up that you know we you know it's possible for women to not just uh lead an office but to uh to to you know give birth in office so yeah that's probably
a
Speaker 31 (lower-pitched voice): positive thing i think
Speaker 35: although you know i have to say also benazia buto and pakistan's in the first so credit where christ
Speaker 13 (lower-pitched voice): you yeah i hadn't realized that um anyway i sort of interrupted you
when
Speaker 13 (lower-pitched voice): you were sort of giving the backstory as to your interest
Speaker 27 (lower-pitched voice): in U.S. politics from a somewhat anomalous perspective, at least geographically.
Yeah,
Speaker 37: right. Well, you know, I don't
Speaker 34: know where it came from. I mean, I learned about American history in my last year of high school. I found it really fascinating
Speaker 17 (lower-pitched voice): that, you know, that I think was part of it. I had two very great teachers, professors in university who were American and they taught
Speaker 31 (lower-pitched voice): American history.
Speaker 31 (lower-pitched voice): at Auckland University who really kind of nurtured students' interest in the subject. And, you know, I
Speaker 17 (lower-pitched voice): ended up for
when I
Speaker 17 (lower-pitched voice): went into grad school, I ended up focusing on U.S. history as part of my, well, as part of my, as my focus. And that's sort of where I guess it sort of began. I mean, I'd always kind of obviously kept
track
Speaker 31 (lower-pitched voice): of what was happening in the U.S., the
U.S.'s
Speaker 31 (lower-pitched voice): one of the more consequential countries in the world, I
Speaker 38: would say. I think that's a pretty uncontroversial point. Well, I mean, the
Speaker 13 (lower-pitched voice): thing that you mentioned about most Americans not being aware that their political affairs are followed pretty closely around the world actually has a foreign policy element to it because Americans are also not aware that the United States is like the world's leading military power.
Speaker 13 (lower-pitched voice): and has a military portfolio that spans literally the entire world. And that ignorance, and I'm not even necessarily rendering judgment on people who are ignorant. It's difficult to keep track of all this. But if you are not even familiar with that function of your government, then it might not occur
Speaker 27 (lower-pitched voice): to you that it would be of interest to people elsewhere.
So I
Speaker 27 (lower-pitched voice): think it's sort of like, it's an interesting...
Speaker 27 (lower-pitched voice): when you put
it that way.
Speaker 29: Yeah, and you know, I mean, I know this fact tends
Speaker 17 (lower-pitched voice): to get kind of overstated sometimes, but I do think that a lot of Americans, because they don't travel
Speaker 23 (lower-pitched voice): tons outside the U.S., and again, you know, this is
a very
Speaker 23 (lower-pitched voice): big generalization, and there's lots of reasons
for it,
Speaker 23 (lower-pitched voice): but I think that kind of limits people's perspective, and you know,
Speaker 17 (lower-pitched voice): I mean I can understand the U.S.
Speaker 17 (lower-pitched voice): massive country um and uh you know it's the size of a
Man 26: continent by itself and uh obviously there's uh countries on either side of it uh as well uh so you know kind of going
Speaker 17 (lower-pitched voice): beyond north america may not seem like uh even even necessary but um you know whereas i think uh for a country like new zealand and you know very much uh
Speaker 17 (lower-pitched voice): Australia as well, because we're, one, we're small, but also the second thing is because we're shunted all the way, you know, on the sort of
Speaker 31 (lower-pitched voice): far corner of the world, away from where all the action is happening,
there is
Speaker 31 (lower-pitched voice): this kind of cultural drive to travel outside of our countries and go to different places and live elsewhere, kind of see the world. And I think that maybe imbues New Zealanders with a
Speaker 39: little more cautiousness that they're
Speaker 39: Part of the world, but not the world, if that makes sense.
Speaker 40 (lower-pitched voice): Right. Because, I mean, you could spend your entire life as a U.S. citizen trying to see just the
Speaker 13 (lower-pitched voice): totality of what exists in the U.S. never be able to do it. Right? So, you know, that's actually something that I've aspired to do, meaning I've visited pretty much every corner of the U.S. with the exception of Hawaii, which I will do at some point. But...
Speaker 13 (lower-pitched voice): The notion of being well-traveled within the U.S. is something that I think maybe doesn't occur to you if you're from
New Zealand,
Speaker 13 (lower-pitched voice): for
Speaker 41 (lower-pitched voice): example, because there's just so
much to
Speaker 41 (lower-pitched voice): see, especially if you want to cover American politics. I mean, it varies regionally, as you know. And so you want to get a lay of the land as comprehensively as possible, which sort of, in a way, precludes...
Speaker 19 (lower-pitched voice): even entertaining becoming well-traveled abroad. At least
Speaker 42: that's how it's sort of worked so far in my experience, although I'm going to try to rectify that at some point.
Yeah, I mean,
Speaker 43: absolutely. It's a massive country. There's
Speaker 44 (lower-pitched voice): huge cultural and social and political differences within different regions, within different states,
Speaker 17 (lower-pitched voice): sometimes inside of different states. So, yeah, I mean, and the amount of stuff to see, I mean, I cannot say
Speaker 31 (lower-pitched voice): that
I
Remotely
Speaker 31 (lower-pitched voice): traveled through most of Even a large fraction of
Speaker 17 (lower-pitched voice): the US but even that
you know
Speaker 17 (lower-pitched voice): The there's like even when you go on one trip for example They're like a hundred things that you would want to
Speaker 36: see that that you want to come back to but then you know If you if you do that You've got every other corner of the country that you have to get to
Speaker 45 (lower-pitched voice): so yeah I you know that I think that that might be part of the reason why I
Speaker 17 (lower-pitched voice): the statistic about Americans, you know, whatever percentage is known possible. So I
Speaker 35: think that might be part of it. I mean, yeah, the U.S. is, I mean, you can maybe tell me this for sure, but I mean, it's
Speaker 46: bigger than Europe physically, I think, right?
If you
Speaker 13 (lower-pitched voice): include Alaska, for sure. I'm not exactly 100% sure on the continental U.S., but I mean, Alaska is
like,
a
Speaker 47 (lower-pitched voice): mini continent in its own right it's kind of insane if you you know compare it on a map with the rest of the u.s
Speaker 13 (lower-pitched voice): land mass um but but yeah it's uh it's an enormous undertaking to
even
Speaker 8 (lower-pitched voice): think that it's within your capacity
to really
Speaker 8 (lower-pitched voice): understand the full range of
Speaker 47 (lower-pitched voice): political sentiments and at least in my case um in in the u.s that's why you know
Speaker 47 (lower-pitched voice): traveling abroad although i've done a little bit but it hasn't has been on much of my hasn't been on my radar as much as it might be if i had grown
up
Speaker 48: in a place like the zealand
Speaker 47 (lower-pitched voice): right yeah
Speaker 35: yeah which i think is fair um and you know i'm not that's basically how i got
Speaker 17 (lower-pitched voice): my start in in journalism uh in general but also in the u.s as i i traveled and i lived in the u.s for uh a year or so and um
Speaker 17 (lower-pitched voice): And yeah, I ended up sort of just getting into journalism that way. So it's kind of funny. In many ways, I know more people and I'm better known in the U.S. than I am in my own home country, which is kind of a hilarious situation to be in.
Speaker 49: Well, if you ever write a memoir, that should be like
Man 50: the animating theme where you sort of try to understand the implications of that for your life trajectory or something.
Yeah,
Speaker 51: yeah. I'm a man without a home. Right. Windswept across the world. And you live in the U.S.
Speaker 52: now, right? I'm
Speaker 53: actually in Canada at the
Speaker 52: moment.
Speaker 54: Yeah, in Toronto. Got it.
All right,
Speaker 55: so let's do some foreign policy here vis-a-vis the presidential campaign. I guess just start with
Speaker 56: a broad question. What
do you think
Speaker 41 (lower-pitched voice): is sort of like the main...
Speaker 41 (lower-pitched voice): axis of disagreement now at least among the leading contenders in the foreign policy domain I mean to the extent that foreign policy has really even been at the forefront of the debate which it kind of hasn't
Speaker 20 (lower-pitched voice): which is
sort of
Speaker 20 (lower-pitched voice): another fault of the process but you'd think like as we mentioned before the country with the world's most powerful military in fact the most powerful military in world's history would have that higher up on the agenda but there's not I mean there's all kinds of clamor
Speaker 20 (lower-pitched voice): for climate change debates and other issue-specific debates, which is all well and good, but there's not much of a constituency to have a foreign policy debate because it kind of
Speaker 57 (lower-pitched voice): maybe raises some uncomfortable questions for certain people. But it does recede into the
Speaker 59: background a
Speaker 58: bit.
Well, there's
Speaker 10: definitely been, you know, American liberals, and this goes back to,
Speaker 17 (lower-pitched voice): you know, well before Trump, I've sort of always
not...
Cared
Speaker 17 (lower-pitched voice): that much about foreign policy They have say during the Bush years although You know once Obama basically just continued Bush's policies are kind of You couldn't help but assume that Maybe uncharitably that a
Man 60: lot of the reason that people cared about foreign policy during Bush's two terms is because They didn't
Speaker 61 (lower-pitched voice): like Bush and it was an effective way to attack him
and
Speaker 61 (lower-pitched voice): Um, maybe that's unfair, but, um, I, I don't know. I, I,
Speaker 30: I would, I would argue for that, but yeah, I think it's fair. Yeah. Okay. That's good. That's good. But, um, well, because it goes back to
Speaker 63: the question, like what happened to the quote unquote anti-war movement when Obama
Speaker 64 (lower-pitched voice): took office, it just totally dissipated, which lends some credence to your, your theory.
Speaker 65: Yeah, I mean, that actually, there was a book or a kind of study, a
Speaker 17 (lower-pitched voice): booklet study that was done about this by an author whose name I can't remember, I actually, I've interviewed him, I've read the book, and that's basically the point that he makes, which is
that
Speaker 17 (lower-pitched voice): The Democratic Party basically co-opted the anti-war energy that was happening on the ground over Bush, and they kind of funneled it into first their midterm victories in 2006, which of course were kind of undercut because it was a huge wave election, and they ended up because of Rahm Emanuel recruiting a bunch of right-wing Democrats, blue dogs, who obviously are very...
Speaker 17 (lower-pitched voice): pro-military, pro-intervention. And then, of course, again, under Obama. Obama campaigned as an anti-war candidate.
Man 60: That was one of the main things to do with his candidacy, why people liked him. It certainly wasn't health care. He didn't have a health care
Speaker 17 (lower-pitched voice): policy for a while. Well, he did have a health care
Speaker 40 (lower-pitched voice): policy. Sorry to interject, but it's funny, actually, to think about this in hindsight. He did have a health care policy. It was a little bit
Speaker 13 (lower-pitched voice): underdeveloped. But the crux of his...
Speaker 13 (lower-pitched voice): Dispute with Hillary Clinton on health care policy in 2008 was that she wanted an individual mandate and he did not. And they sort of were at each other's
Speaker 63: throats for several months over that pretty narrow distinction that ended up being utterly meaningless because Obamacare.
Speaker 63: Included the image of the the individual mandate regardless. So like the entire
Speaker 40 (lower-pitched voice): health care debate that transpired over many months in the 2008 primary cycle ended up just being negated and was like much ado about
Speaker 13 (lower-pitched voice): nothing.
Oh, the
Speaker 66: Democrats. Yeah. Yeah. And just to clarify what I meant
Speaker 23 (lower-pitched voice): was just
a.
I
Speaker 23 (lower-pitched voice): don't know the exact time period, but it was when there was still, I think, John Edwards in the race, and
Speaker 31 (lower-pitched voice): for a while, Obama didn't really have any clear-cut health policy, and then it became this big flashpoint, and he sort of had to take it up. Ryan Grimm writes about this in his recent book, but you're absolutely right, yeah, during the
Speaker 17 (lower-pitched voice): debates between Obama and Clinton, that was a major flashpoint, which...
It
Speaker 17 (lower-pitched voice): didn't matter whatsoever, ultimately, but it would
Speaker 67: have been a little
Speaker 12: boring to say, we'll just figure it out once Congress takes over like
Speaker 64 (lower-pitched voice): that. Would have lent itself to a really heated debate over the course of 26 televised forums and stuff.
Speaker 10: Yeah. Yeah. Or, you know, saying like, well, listen, I'll have to figure this out once I've talked to all the representatives from the health insurance
Speaker 68 (lower-pitched voice): industry. I'm not totally sure. We
Speaker 69: have to wait for Joe Lieberman to weigh in. But, you
Speaker 70: know,
Speaker 64 (lower-pitched voice): which is like literally what happened. I mean, Joe Lieberman killed the public option. I mean, maybe maybe the people listening don't recall this because they're too young or whatever. But Joe Lieberman is not.
Speaker 64 (lower-pitched voice): He's
Speaker 27 (lower-pitched voice): regarded as a
Speaker 64 (lower-pitched voice): villain for good
Speaker 27 (lower-pitched voice): reason because he like almost single-handedly vetoed the public option from the ultimate Obamacare bill as a condition
Speaker 71 (lower-pitched voice): of his support.
Speaker 45 (lower-pitched voice): Absolutely. And his son is now
Speaker 10: running for Senate. The administration didn't punish him. They could have
Speaker 17 (lower-pitched voice): punished him by taking away his place on a committee or down-ranking him, but they didn't. They just kind of let them destroy
Speaker 35: it, which maybe
Speaker 35: suggest that they weren't really that committed
Speaker 73: to, you know, a more robust health care
Speaker 66: reform anyway. But yeah, I mean, besides that, I mean, the thing that really made people excited about Obama, that
Speaker 17 (lower-pitched voice): was the main point of difference between him and Clinton, besides this individual mandate thing, was that...
Speaker 17 (lower-pitched voice): Obama had voted or not he hadn't voted, but he had opposed the Iraq war early on But obviously Hillary Clinton had voted for it. I think so had John Edwards obviously Joe
Speaker 44 (lower-pitched voice): Biden had so
Speaker 74: but John
Speaker 75: Edwards actually recanted
and
Speaker 8 (lower-pitched voice): that vote much quicker than anybody else not that I really matters that much in terms of his judgment during a pivotal moment but he at least attempted to distinguish himself by relatively quickly repudiating the vote and saying it
was
Man 50: a mistake and etc whereas
Speaker 76: for Hillary
Speaker 13 (lower-pitched voice): Hillary didn't admit it was a mistake until 2014 so it took her 12 years literally
Yeah.
Speaker 10: Well, you know, it wasn't clear until 2014 whether it had gone wrong or not. When she just so happened
to
Speaker 77: have a new book coming out and was preparing for another presidential campaign.
Right.
Speaker 10: Yeah, exactly. And I think, to be honest, I mean, even Obama's opposition to the Iraq war is overstated. I can't remember where I read this, but
Speaker 17 (lower-pitched voice): there was indication that actually he wasn't that
–
Speaker 17 (lower-pitched voice): Anti the Iraq war. I think he had told someone that actually if he had, well, you know what, this is in, I remember where this is in. This is in a book that came out this year called A Crisis Wasted. That's written by...
you
Speaker 17 (lower-pitched voice): know the book okay so and this guy the guy who wrote it he's a democratic insider um long time you know he was a clinton clinton guy he was involved in a transition and he talks about how he remembers interviewing obama um i think it was in 2004 or 2005 or something and obama basically said to him that you know like if if he had been in congress
um
Speaker 17 (lower-pitched voice): When the vote had actually been up he probably would have voted for the Iraq war so you know Obama's Obama got lucky because he did oppose it Publicly eventually and he was able to you know, he didn't he didn't have to have a vote which which which Left him able to avoid kind of making a tough decision there You know does he does he go for the right thing or does he kind of join in the rest of the crowd and the Iraq war Hillary Clinton?
Speaker 17 (lower-pitched voice): biden all these other guys um they they didn't have that choice they didn't have that luxury they had to vote uh and they voted
Speaker 25: poorly obviously yeah
but uh i think
Speaker 79: you asked me we're on a very uh long tangent there but yeah that's okay
Speaker 78: we're on a we're on a we're doing
Speaker 80 (lower-pitched voice): a we we do it we do things in a roundabout manner on this this podcast so okay
Speaker 81: that's totally fine um so
well to to
Speaker 82: answer your
Speaker 34: question um
Speaker 34: I think, you know, I think the candidates realize that the U.S. public has a lot less tolerance for foreign
Speaker 17 (lower-pitched voice): interventions, or at least, you know, sort of out and out foreign interventions. People are still happy if there's, you know, special forces being deported around the world that they don't hear about.
Speaker 17 (lower-pitched voice): But certainly, yeah, you know, actual wars, I think there's a sense that the American public is tired of all this kind of thing. So I think that isn't as much
of a
Speaker 17 (lower-pitched voice): point
Speaker 34: of differentiation anymore. I think, you know, even pretty much every candidate is now talking about
Speaker 83 (lower-pitched voice): withdrawing from Afghanistan, although there is obviously a difference there between candidates about
Afghanistan.
how
Speaker 83 (lower-pitched voice): fast they would withdraw,
Speaker 17 (lower-pitched voice): whether they leave forces behind, and so on and so forth. I think one of the big differences... And there's also
Speaker 40 (lower-pitched voice): a difference in terms of how committal
Speaker 8 (lower-pitched voice): they are in terms of like a timeline. Would a residual force be left, which are all kind of like weasel words to
Man 50: basically just continue the status quo, because Obama had also ostensibly committed to...
Man 50: withdrawing from Afghanistan and it didn't ultimately matter because there was enough of a quote unquote residual force left behind that you could just as easily do a surge and then it's like nothing happened
Speaker 84: right yeah yeah yeah exactly and but I would say the other major difference
Speaker 68 (lower-pitched voice): it's really shaping up between you know different camps of candidates is the issue of Israel I mean that
is
Speaker 68 (lower-pitched voice): So, U.S. support for Israel has really been non-negotiable for decades, and we are starting to finally see some actual daylight creeping in here. Obviously, I think it's most traumatic with Sanders. Sanders is the only candidate that has said that he would condition.
Speaker 68 (lower-pitched voice): U.S. aid to Israel, or use that as a kind of point of leverage to change
Man 60: their behavior. I know some other candidates
Speaker 85: have said similar things, like
Man 60: Pete Burjage, in his answer to
the
Speaker 68 (lower-pitched voice): Council on Foreign Relations, he said that, you know, he would consider maybe cutting some of the aid if Israel annexed the West Bank, but that,
Speaker 17 (lower-pitched voice): you know, that's a far, you
I
Speaker 17 (lower-pitched voice): would say that's a far different policy than what Sanders is talking about, which is actually whether they annex the West Bank
Speaker 68 (lower-pitched voice): or not, using the aid as a sort of way to make Israel change its behavior, maybe sit down to talks, who
Speaker 17 (lower-pitched voice): knows what else. So I think that's a really big thing. You look at the Democratic electorate right now, the Democratic voting population anyway is more on the side of Palestinians than it has been.
In a
Speaker 17 (lower-pitched voice): very long time, it's increasingly not viewed as politically risky to speak out against Israel and the actions of Israel's government. Obviously, you know, there's
Speaker 68 (lower-pitched voice): pushback on this, as we know, from the stuff with Ilhan Oma and the quote unquote squad. They've yeah, I know,
Speaker 86: they've received.
Speaker 87: Thank you for inserting scare quotes there.
Speaker 86: But
Speaker 10: yeah, they've received a lot of pushback obviously from the right and the center, the so-called center. So it's not like this question is settled or anything, but I think that you can see
Speaker 44 (lower-pitched voice): the candidates increasingly bolder in terms of criticizing Israel.
I
Speaker 17 (lower-pitched voice): think part of that comes down to donors. I really think a lot of...
The
Speaker 17 (lower-pitched voice): candidates are just worried about, regardless of what they believe, and even if they see that things are changing, at least in voter attitudes, I think they are kind of wary of
Speaker 44 (lower-pitched voice): alienating donors who view Israel as one of their big issues. You
know one thing I
Speaker 13 (lower-pitched voice): wonder about that is if Netanyahu is forced from office, which is far from certain, he may be able to put together a government. We don't know.
Speaker 13 (lower-pitched voice): but if Netanyahu is no longer in the picture and you had a more centrist or even center-left I don't know exactly how one would describe Gantz ideologically but at least less
to the
Speaker 13 (lower-pitched voice): right than Netanyahu at minimum I sort of wonder how that would factor into how the
Speaker 40 (lower-pitched voice): Democratic candidates speak about Israel because
Speaker 40 (lower-pitched voice): usually they reserve
Speaker 88 (lower-pitched voice): theirire for Netanyahu specifically because they can tie him to Trump, they can tie him to like right-wing movements globally, right? They can use him as sort of a stand-in so as to not necessarily question some of the underlying premises of how the state has operated forever, essentially. So I kind of wonder if their rhetoric would soften if somebody who is a little more amenable
Speaker 89: became Prime Minister, right?
Yeah, I think
Speaker 10: that's a good question
Speaker 17 (lower-pitched voice): because, I mean, you know, obviously, at least based on what I understand, Gantz isn't really that different from Netanyahu, at least in foreign policy. I mean, he's just as kind of right-wing
Speaker 31 (lower-pitched voice): and militaristic, maybe with a few little changes here and there. But basically, it's the same policy.
But
Speaker 17 (lower-pitched voice): you're right in that.
Speaker 17 (lower-pitched voice): Um, there, there would probably be a, uh, a tendency to, to maybe not really acknowledge this or even
see
Man 26: this because, uh, you know, he's, he's liberal on other fronts and therefore, you know, people just sort
of assume
Man 26: that he must be liberal. Uh, also when it comes to how he, you know,
Speaker 17 (lower-pitched voice): what it was, uh, what has,
uh, what has, uh,
Speaker 17 (lower-pitched voice): position is in treating Palestinians. So yeah, that pressure could evaporate
Speaker 35: away, depending
Speaker 10: on what happens.
So I
Speaker 10: guess we'll have to see.
But I
Speaker 10: think there still is, even though Netanyahu is the
Speaker 17 (lower-pitched voice): face of Israel right now and has been for a long time, and obviously is this very blatantly villainous face, I think that all it would take is yet another
kind of
Speaker 17 (lower-pitched voice): crisis you know another another instance of Israeli soldiers
Speaker 31 (lower-pitched voice): murdering journalists and and maiming people by shooting them in the legs killing you know I don't protest is that kind of thing and
Man 26: and you know I think people would sort of realize that no matter who you
Speaker 17 (lower-pitched voice): swap out as a leader of Israel that this particular element of its policy is kind of basically stay the
Speaker 9: same
mm-hmm
And
Speaker 9: then just to finish on that, I think the last thing I
Speaker 23 (lower-pitched voice): would say that I've seen as a kind of emerging distinction is
Speaker 17 (lower-pitched voice): Warren and Sanders have both been critical of the War on Terror. Sanders did that speech I think in 2017 where he basically just – he said the War on Terror was a failure. He criticized kind of every element of it that we basically had to change course and do something completely different.
Speaker 17 (lower-pitched voice): Um, Warren, Warren hasn't gone quite as far as he has, but she's, um, said things along those lines of basically, you know, just bombing
Speaker 31 (lower-pitched voice): people into oblivion forever and ever is not really a sustainable or effective solution to what is happening in the world. Um, and I haven't seen that
Speaker 17 (lower-pitched voice): from a lot of the other candidates. Um, I can't think of anyone really who has articulated that. So I think that's another,
you know, I think that's another,
Speaker 17 (lower-pitched voice): Difference how important it's going to be in the election. I can't say like you said foreign policy hasn't really come up as a particularly
Man 60: Big topic in this election despite the fact that obviously the u.s. President has more power to shape foreign policy than anything else
Speaker 46: So I will
say You
Speaker 91: know, I think it's one thing I know the
Speaker 13 (lower-pitched voice): speech that you're referring to from Sanders in 2017 But at least in terms of your paraphrase of the war in common I sort of wonder
Speaker 13 (lower-pitched voice): How
Speaker 41 (lower-pitched voice): to think about that, because it's one thing to say, no, we can't keep up bombing our way out of problems for in perpetuity.
Speaker 88 (lower-pitched voice): But it's another to say we are going to cease bombing these particular locales like Somalia, for example,
Speaker 57 (lower-pitched voice): which we've been bombing regularly for years. I don't know that you would necessarily get a commitment from Warren or perhaps even Sanders to...
Speaker 57 (lower-pitched voice): refrain from all bombing of a particular country because it's futile right i think that i think it's much easier to talk about it in the abstract whereas there's always going to be somebody who says oh if a certain terrorist or something shows up in mogadishu on the outskirts somewhere you gotta bomb right so it's a it's a it's a little bit more uh difficult
Speaker 92 (lower-pitched voice): when you when you get into specifics and i think
Speaker 92 (lower-pitched voice): What
Speaker 8 (lower-pitched voice): tends to be done is that specifics are avoided in foreign policy, so the candidates can give themselves as much latitude as possible when they're actually in a
Man 50: position of power to make those decisions.
Yeah, I
Speaker 9: think that's right. I think that whatever president ends up being elected,
Speaker 17 (lower-pitched voice): presumably a non-Trump president, I think whoever they are, there will have to be some significant pushback
Speaker 31 (lower-pitched voice): and challenge by the left, but hopefully not just the left, people in general
Speaker 17 (lower-pitched voice): who are committed to
it.
Speaker 17 (lower-pitched voice): Ending wars and ending kind of the senseless slaughter of people around the world Because I think it's one of those things
Speaker 31 (lower-pitched voice): that it's just very easy to not do anything about if you're president It's very easy, especially when you're hearing, you know, all manner
of kind of
Speaker 31 (lower-pitched voice): scare
Man 60: stories from people in the military about you know what will happen if you oh if you stop you know uh if you if you start bombing somalia or like uh if you get rid of that air base in
Speaker 17 (lower-pitched voice): jibouti or like whatever it's very easy to um to just listen to that and go well you know i'm getting pushback from there
Speaker 31 (lower-pitched voice): i'm not getting pushback from anyone else i'm not getting pushback from my voters so why am i going to take a political risk and actually get
Speaker 17 (lower-pitched voice): rid of this stuff So yeah, I think whoever gets elected, even if it's Sanders, even if he has promised
Speaker 17 (lower-pitched voice): to sort
Speaker 23 (lower-pitched voice): of change or reorient away from the war on terror, which I think is genuine, but again the realities, the political realities are
Speaker 17 (lower-pitched voice): something that can come in and basically grind those efforts to a halt, and people have to keep holding their feet to the fire on that. Yeah,
I
Speaker 63: mean, I think the
Speaker 13 (lower-pitched voice): lack of specificity is most conspicuous with Warren, who, although she has made some commitments here and there, like she has been, as clear as you could be, I would think, that
Speaker 41 (lower-pitched voice): she favors withdrawing troops from Afghanistan immediately although she of course wants to leave some be
Speaker 93: behind some kind of like
I think she
Speaker 41 (lower-pitched voice): said she wants to leave
Speaker 93: behind I have the quote here hold on a second she said
Speaker 94 (lower-pitched voice): we should redouble our efforts to support the Afghan government and civil society as they were to promote the rule of law combat corruption in the narcotics trade which reads to me that
Speaker 94 (lower-pitched voice): She's gonna leave behind some combat troops because
Speaker 41 (lower-pitched voice): if you want u.s. Forces to be involved in all those functions It was would probably necessarily entail Some
form of
Speaker 41 (lower-pitched voice): combat at some point
right
Speaker 95: if you want if like you're if you're Saying
Speaker 21 (lower-pitched voice): that it's it's within the u.s. Purview to combat the narcotics trade I mean, do you think that
Speaker 13 (lower-pitched voice): the narcotics trade is conducted with you know?
Speaker 13 (lower-pitched voice): flowers and bunny rabbits. No, that's probably going to entail probably the
Speaker 71 (lower-pitched voice): exchange of gunfire at some point.
Right.
Speaker 45 (lower-pitched voice): Yeah. And, um, I mean, Warren's climate plan or part of a climate
Speaker 61 (lower-pitched voice): plan, which
Man 60: was basically just to, um, to kind of greenify the military, but essentially maintain the, uh, the huge
Speaker 17 (lower-pitched voice): presence that the U S has overseas, um, which is a far,
um,
Speaker 17 (lower-pitched voice): greater contributed to climate change than, you know, the fact that bases and stuff aren't green. I think that sort of suggests that she, it's probably not
Speaker 96 (lower-pitched voice): saying that she's going to really be looking at
Speaker 73: too much. I
Speaker 96 (lower-pitched voice): mean, you know, you can look at some previous votes and people's record. I mean, Sanders vote against John Brennan,
Man 60: of course.
Who
Man 60: was famous for basically, you know, being the the kind of architect of Obama's drone
Speaker 17 (lower-pitched voice): policy Warren did vote for him you know, I'm not saying that that means that Sanders is gonna Do a radical turn away from from
Man 60: the existing drone policy and in fact if you read some of his public statements, it seems clear that he's gonna maintain That's definitely what he said in
Speaker 31 (lower-pitched voice): 2016. You know, I haven't seen anything I
That
Speaker 31 (lower-pitched voice): says otherwise that he wouldn't keep it going. Brennan,
Speaker 97: by the way, also the architect of Russiagate, arguably, but that's another issue.
Yes,
Speaker 96 (lower-pitched voice): very much. If not the architect, I would say certainly one of the main kind of
Speaker 31 (lower-pitched voice): proponents. One of the main
Speaker 98: propagandists kind of
Speaker 31 (lower-pitched voice): going on CNN and other shows and pushing that narrative for many years.
Speaker 31 (lower-pitched voice): which, yeah, I
Speaker 35: would say that there's an interesting connection there. But, yeah, so I think
Speaker 10: when
it comes
Speaker 10: to that kind of thing, I mean, yeah, probably all of the candidates have been super specific.
Speaker 10: But, you know, I mean, I do
Speaker 23 (lower-pitched voice): think Sanders has gone further than the other ones. And again, people have to make sure that he actually lives up to his word. But if he really is intent on taking on climate change, I mean, it's just indisputable. The U.S. cannot maintain the.
Speaker 23 (lower-pitched voice): Massive global footprint
Speaker 100: it has now and and actually Get what we need to be when it comes to carbon emissions. Yeah,
you were
Speaker 28: actually fairly critical in
Speaker 8 (lower-pitched voice): much of what you wrote about Sanders in terms of foreign policy during and I think and then after I think the
Speaker 27 (lower-pitched voice): the 2016 campaign I Actually have a quote from one of your 2017 pieces. He said that his
Speaker 41 (lower-pitched voice): quote relative silence
is
Speaker 41 (lower-pitched voice): Obama's foreign policy has mirrored
Speaker 94 (lower-pitched voice): his fairly conventional foreign policy thinking throughout his
Speaker 27 (lower-pitched voice): Washington career and you contrasted that with Jeremy Corbyn who you think thought was a more ideal exemplar of how to challenge convention in the foreign
Speaker 101: policy arena I mean do you think that you think of that 2017 speech which I think came later
Speaker 41 (lower-pitched voice): and other subsequent developments have sort of cut against what you said there and in 2017 or how do you think about
it now?
Speaker 34: Yeah, yeah. I definitely feel far as harshly towards my foreign policy now, not just because of that
Speaker 103 (lower-pitched voice): speech, but you had some of the stuff like his role, really the leading role in making the willpower's vote on Yemen happen. That was a
Speaker 104 (lower-pitched voice): really big thing, I think not just because it showed that he had...
Speaker 104 (lower-pitched voice): growing and perhaps seeing that there was political space for him to go back to his more kind of anti-war roots. I mean, one of the things I will say, I was a little unfair about him in that original piece was that I didn't talk about some of the very good stances he took over the Reagan
Speaker 44 (lower-pitched voice): administration's Nicaragua policy, for example, and other elements of U.S. foreign policy during the 80s, which I think is important to know. -
When
Speaker 105: he was in a municipal role, granted.
Speaker 10: Yeah, exactly. So very, very different set of pressures there, of course, and the fact that he
Speaker 104 (lower-pitched voice): kind of went more towards the center once he went into a more national role, I think, showed that ultimately, you know, his priority wasn't as much foreign policy as some
Speaker 83 (lower-pitched voice): of the more domestic stuff. But
I
Speaker 104 (lower-pitched voice): think he has been showing, if nothing else, as a kind of point of...
Speaker 104 (lower-pitched voice): distinction between him and some of the other candidates and maybe also to kind of show that he is able to work within the system to get things done.
He has shown more
Speaker 104 (lower-pitched voice): proclivity
Speaker 106: to kind of more anti-war, anti-interventionist stances
Speaker 44 (lower-pitched voice): and you know I mean the vote against John Brennan I think is significant. I think it does tell us that even
Speaker 104 (lower-pitched voice): Sanders' worst is still
Speaker 104 (lower-pitched voice): uh, still has an understanding of, you know, what the correct foreign policy should be, even if he may need, um, some nudging, uh, from, from, uh, the left and other groups to get there. Um, but yeah, I, I, I don't,
Speaker 107 (lower-pitched voice): I think he has, he's done a lot better. I think, you know, the hiring of Matt Duss, for example,
Speaker 10: uh, is a really good indication of where he wants to go on foreign policy. Um, I think the other thing, the thing that really impressed me with
Speaker 104 (lower-pitched voice): Sanders in front of policy is and I have not seen any other candidates say this.
As far as I
Speaker 104 (lower-pitched voice): know he's the only one who's actually articulated this sanz is the
Speaker 17 (lower-pitched voice): only person that seems to recognize the reality of the world that we're looking at right now which is there's a world that is
Speaker 104 (lower-pitched voice): being increasingly divided by um by kind of neoliberal authoritarians whether it's trump bolsonaro uh orban then
Speaker 44 (lower-pitched voice): yahoo and you know so on and so forth uh obviously boris johnson in the
how
Speaker 104 (lower-pitched voice): exactly he would govern on the world stage, we haven't really gone to fully see because the Brexit debacle has kind of dominated that. But Sanders really recognizes that. He sees that there's a really dangerous global movement and he understands the need to make international linkages to fight against that. Obviously, Sanders and Corbyn have a...
Speaker 104 (lower-pitched voice): A not not a silly intimate relationship, but they have a relationship. I think they they see each other as kind of Kind of fighting for the same common cause I think
Speaker 80 (lower-pitched voice): it's a little bit overstated though. I mean, I get the point and I think there's something to it obviously but
And this is something that
Speaker 80 (lower-pitched voice): you
Speaker 13 (lower-pitched voice): actually hear espoused often in the media and in other discussions on just the international scene, but
I
Speaker 13 (lower-pitched voice): Something has always sort of or to me about this sort of easy conflation of Political phenomena as discrepant as a full scenario and a Trump and a Boris Johnson. I mean it seems like those are just the people who have to be in power and
Speaker 63: it's
Suitable for
Speaker 92 (lower-pitched voice): narrative purposes to kind of put them into this same sort of
Speaker 27 (lower-pitched voice): nebulous category of neoliberal authoritarianism, which I think admittedly is a little bit vague and
I
Speaker 27 (lower-pitched voice): don't
Speaker 108 (lower-pitched voice): know, something about that seems like a little bit of an oversimplification to me, which doesn't preclude taking steps internationally to forge certain alliances to combat some of the more, you know,
Speaker 92 (lower-pitched voice): maybe noxious developments. But something about that doesn't sit quite right with me.
Well, I mean, we
Speaker 104 (lower-pitched voice): can argue about the labels, but I think it's pretty...
Speaker 104 (lower-pitched voice): are incontrovertible that, you know, a guy like Bolsonaro and Trump, for example, I mean, that was a very similar phenomenon taking place in both countries, which is you've got governments.
Speaker 8 (lower-pitched voice): Glenn Greenwald vociferously denies that they are meaningfully similar, at least in the way that
Man 50: a lot of
Man 50: us pundits try to assert but anyway
well
Speaker 104 (lower-pitched voice): they're different in this sense which is that bolsonaro i think is personally a far more committed right-wing counter-revolutionary um and and someone who is far more actually committed to being uh an authoritarian or even a despot uh trump trump i think kind of like flails around but in both cases you do have governments that are staffed with people um whose goal at various times has been to basically roll back um the tide to the
left.
Speaker 104 (lower-pitched voice): uh, in, in both North and South America. Um, you know, I mean, the Trump boy was trying to do in Venezuela didn't work out, but you know, it's no surprise that the people who are trying to stuff on the previous presidents, uh, are in the Trump. And I think a more concerning, um, uh, development and commonality, uh, commonality between those two guys is that you have in both cases, this
is a,
Speaker 104 (lower-pitched voice): Basically, a neoliberal government that is attempting to, one, it takes a very kind of violent approach to, say, minorities in those countries. But I think, secondly, it's also really just trying to ponder the world's resources at a very precarious moment when we are rapidly running out of time to forge a worldwide challenge.
Speaker 104 (lower-pitched voice): united effort to combat the easily the greatest threat that humanity has ever faced on this earth and both of them are basically just throwing logs onto the fire throwing logs and gasoline onto the fire that they do not care about that they're
just sort of
Speaker 104 (lower-pitched voice): trying to exploit as much as possible these last windling moments before we can actually get together and do something about it so i think that's a really important point um yeah i mean uh is uh
I
Speaker 104 (lower-pitched voice): don't know if you describe Netanyahu in the same way, but obviously Netanyahu, he can see which side of the bread is bad on. He's trying to make alliances with these guys. And I think even if Netanyahu doesn't have the same kind of ecocidal motives as the Trump and Bolsonaro governments does.
Speaker 104 (lower-pitched voice): think he does realize that he can make common cause with these guys That you know, they see the world in a in a similar way and and also that He can he can get protection from them Around, you know, especially in a world that is rapidly turning it turning against the Israeli government So I think
Speaker 109: it's important to realize that and I think to be honest Other than Sanders a few speeches. I've
Speaker 10: seen on this I don't know if anyone even realizes this. I don't know if anyone realizes that that
You
Speaker 10: know, the only way that we're actually going to solve the climate crisis,
Speaker 104 (lower-pitched voice): which, as far as
Speaker 44 (lower-pitched voice): I'm concerned, should be the organizing principle of not just U.S. foreign policy, but global foreign policy. The
Speaker 104 (lower-pitched voice): only way we're going to get through it is if we find a way to deal with people like Bolsonaro and Trump and, you know, Scott Morrison in Australia, for example, who isn't kind of authoritarian or anything, but very much in the same vein as kind of just
this...
Speaker 104 (lower-pitched voice): you know, late stage kind of neoliberal plunderer. So I wish that, I wish that this was talked about more than, you know, oh, Iran might get a nuclear weapon, which, you know, if Iran had a nuke, it would not change anything. It really wouldn't. I mean, one nuke, Israel has something like 300. Although we don't know because Israel's totally
Speaker 104 (lower-pitched voice): secret about how many nukes it has and what its capabilities are so yeah I think that is the biggest threat
and I
Speaker 104 (lower-pitched voice): wish that we talked about it more in the discourse One
Speaker 110: more
Speaker 56: point on Sanders,
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): I actually went back and watched a couple segments from the 2016 primaries that were foreign policy focused between Hillary and Bernie and I hadn't remembered this but
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): At a certain point when Hillary at
Speaker 88 (lower-pitched voice): least began to perceive Bernie as something of a threat such that she had to formulate talking points and arguments to counter him, she began saying
Speaker 94 (lower-pitched voice): that although it was true that she did vote for the 2002
Iraq War
Speaker 94 (lower-pitched voice): Authorization,
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): Bernie had voted for the Iraq Liberation
Act in
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): 1998, which...
Was
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): then cited as part of the justification for the the war resolution and I
Speaker 13 (lower-pitched voice): hadn't
realized that
Speaker 13 (lower-pitched voice): she had actually been talking about that and it's actually not a bad point and it goes to
the
Speaker 88 (lower-pitched voice): sort of critique that you were laying out at least in 2017 about him in the earlier part of his career kind of being somewhat ensconced in conventional wisdom foreign policy wise where he apparently didn't perceive -
I don't believe.
Speaker 88 (lower-pitched voice): That passing such an act, meaning the Iraq Liberation Act, which essentially codified a call for regime change in terms of the U.S. code, could
be
Speaker 8 (lower-pitched voice): used later on, in this case just four years later, to initiate a war. So to me, that's actually one of the more
Speaker 27 (lower-pitched voice): glaring examples that if you're not familiar with the history, you might not be aware of.
Speaker 9: Yeah, I think that is a really important
Speaker 17 (lower-pitched voice): thing. And obviously, when Sanders says that he led the effort against the Iraq war, obviously that's a slightly incomplete record. There's more to it than that. I do think that there is a major difference between passing that act. Even as significant as it was, though I could be wrong, I think there is a difference between that and then in 2002, in an administration that had made very clear that
Our
Speaker 17 (lower-pitched voice): policy is going to be getting rid of Saddam and this is the thing that we are focusing on. We're going to launch
a very
Speaker 17 (lower-pitched voice): sophisticated campaign to try
Speaker 23 (lower-pitched voice): and get everyone on board. And when it actually comes down to voting for the authorization for that war, whether you vote yes
Speaker 17 (lower-pitched voice): or no, I think that is an important distinction. Oh, sure. It's an important
Speaker 111 (lower-pitched voice): distinction. I'm just saying that at least the narrow point that Hillary was making there in trying to, in some
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): sense, implicate Bernie in the policy trajectory that led to the vote is.
had
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): some validity to it, even if it didn't at all compare with her role, which was hugely significant in her capacity in the
Speaker 27 (lower-pitched voice): Senate.
Yeah, well, you
Speaker 43: know, this shows you how things have changed since since
Speaker 17 (lower-pitched voice): even even, you know, 2015, 2016, which is that I think Sanders didn't really.
care
Speaker 23 (lower-pitched voice): that much about foreign policy or at least he didn't think it was anything that was worth focusing on. I think he just wanted to kind of get his message about inequality and
Speaker 17 (lower-pitched voice): corruption and climate change and everything else out there. And I think the increased, one, I think the fact that Trump won the Republican nomination on the back
of,
Speaker 112: you
Speaker 23 (lower-pitched voice): know, disingenuous, but
The
Speaker 23 (lower-pitched voice): kind of anti-war rhetoric, criticizing Bush and criticizing the Iraq War, and at one point even saying that Libya was a mistake, even though we know that he said at the time that it was the right thing to do. But nonetheless,
Speaker 17 (lower-pitched voice): this is what people thought about him. This is what he was saying when he was most…
Speaker 17 (lower-pitched voice): visible on the in the public arena to a lot of people and i think
Speaker 113: the fact that he won by that and you know by the way there's a study that was done in i think 2017
Speaker 114: or 2018 that um looked at some of these counties that trump had won and those key uh blue states that had switched um and a
Speaker 68 (lower-pitched voice): lot of those places had uh kind of a much remarkably higher number of
Speaker 17 (lower-pitched voice): people who had died uh whether and the rocker of
Speaker 17 (lower-pitched voice): Afghanistan, which may have been part of the thing
Speaker 23 (lower-pitched voice): that turned people away from Clinton towards Trump. Who knows? But I think all of that, coupled with a renewed role for the left in U.S. public life, I think all that has given Sanders, one, it's been a hint to be like, hey, this is something that you should take seriously and focus on, and this is important. And I think it's also given him the space to kind of...
Go and
Speaker 23 (lower-pitched voice): kind of really pursue a
Speaker 17 (lower-pitched voice): much more anti-interventionist foreign policy and and make these critiques of you know I mean he now always puts the military industrial complex as part of his kind of Stump speech
Speaker 23 (lower-pitched voice): list of enemies that he's taking on. So yeah, I mean again, it just shows leaders are important, but also there has to be a
a
Speaker 23 (lower-pitched voice): wider
Speaker 68 (lower-pitched voice): movement that's kind of, kind of behind them and,
and
Speaker 115: forcing them to do what they need to do.
One thing that
Speaker 116: frustrates me is that Bernie will occasionally bring up
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): that Biden voted for the Iraq war. And he contrasts that to his leading the opposition, as he calls it,
which is
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): essentially the same thing you said about Hillary in the
Speaker 40 (lower-pitched voice): previous cycle. And,
Speaker 40 (lower-pitched voice): I just don't know how salient of an attack that is anymore with so much time having passed. What I think ought
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): to be said, and you've written on this, is that Biden is just blatantly misrepresenting his role in 2002, 2003 in the run up to the Iraq war. Not only did he vote for the war, he held hearings that essentially bolstered the Bush administration's case for the war in the
Speaker 13 (lower-pitched voice): Senate. He repeated many of the
topics
Speaker 13 (lower-pitched voice): points that were coming out of the administration i actually interviewed him a couple like a month or so ago now in new hampshire and he claimed to me personally that he opposed the the
Speaker 63: war before it began so he had said at one point that he opposed it like shortly after or like maybe you know right away uh but then he kind of changed his story to me and said he opposed
Speaker 111 (lower-pitched voice): it before which is like just so easily falsifiable, it's crazy.
Speaker 111 (lower-pitched voice): So I kind of wish Sanders and others would not
Speaker 13 (lower-pitched voice): just let him get away with saying that he voted for the war and maybe it wasn't a great idea, but that he's distorting the history and
Speaker 117: misrepresenting what his role was now. So not in 2002, but currently.
Speaker 118: yeah i mean i would love to hear that interview um
Speaker 17 (lower-pitched voice): because uh this is also one of my frustrations it's that uh i i don't understand why they're not calling that out you know well yeah
Speaker 10: it's very possible they haven't read my piece um but uh you know well if any sanders person or you know any other
Speaker 23 (lower-pitched voice): candidate is listening to this uh you know read the piece and then and then
Speaker 23 (lower-pitched voice): Ask Biden about it. You can read my piece
Speaker 119: on Biden, too, where I document what he said. There we go. So we
Speaker 120: can help out. Come to us. We'll help.
Speaker 65: Exactly. Yeah, because you're right. The way that it's presented
Speaker 10: now and all the candidates, whether they realize it or not, they're kind of feeding into this lie is
that.
So
Speaker 10: Biden, it sounds like he was just sort
Speaker 23 (lower-pitched voice): of in the Senate when this came up for a vote and he was kind of, you know, agonizing, oh, what do I do? What do I do? And he decided that he would vote for it and, you know, it was a mistake. Whoops. You know, the shit happens sometimes. Sometimes hundreds of thousands of civilians in another country die. I mean,
Speaker 10: that's already damning enough, but then you consider the fact if you actually look at it.
Speaker 10: Biden's utterances,
Speaker 23 (lower-pitched voice): as you've alluded to, he was on the Sunday talk shows basically repeating Bush rhetoric about the need to get rid of Saddam, how there was no possible avenue for peace with Saddam, how the only thing that could be done is to get rid of him. If he's there in five years, that's a big failure. He obviously voted for the Iraq war. The idea that he opposed it
Speaker 23 (lower-pitched voice): just before it started is complete nonsense he actually traveled
Speaker 17 (lower-pitched voice): around uh europe and the middle east a few months before the war started basically trying to gather support for the coming war if you know he went to israel he went to jordan jordan was not
Speaker 17 (lower-pitched voice): happy about Bush's plans to invade Iraq. Biden basically went there I think basically to kind of soothe things and try and get their
Speaker 23 (lower-pitched voice): buy-in on the coming invasion. He went and talked to the Kurdish parliament and he told them
you
Speaker 23 (lower-pitched voice): know, you have a freight in the US, you know, we're going to make sure that you're liberated, which is a pretty clear, you know,
Speaker 121: indication that, that he knew that a war was coming. He also talked to on the day, sorry to interrupt, but
Speaker 13 (lower-pitched voice): I'm going to, this drives me crazy and I'm going to explode if I don't say it, but because on the day that Colin Powell gave his infamous
address
Speaker 41 (lower-pitched voice): to the UN about weapons of mass destruction, Biden said,
who
Speaker 41 (lower-pitched voice): at that point was the chairman of the Senate Foreign Relations Committee,
gave a
Speaker 41 (lower-pitched voice): press conference.
Speaker 122 (lower-pitched voice): And that
was a
Speaker 122 (lower-pitched voice): crucial moment because he supported everything that Colin Powell said without reservation. So he gave it a bipartisan endorsement, essentially.
And not
Speaker 111 (lower-pitched voice): only that, he explicitly drew a connection between Saddam Hussein and al-Qaeda. So the most egregious
Speaker 122 (lower-pitched voice): talking point
that
Speaker 20 (lower-pitched voice): was being used to Fear Monger was,
Speaker 20 (lower-pitched voice): biden repeated at the most pivotal moment in the lead up to the war so you know it just again that's
why i
Speaker 20 (lower-pitched voice): said it's so easily falsifiable the notion that he opposed it before it began that it's almost preposterous it
is and he as uh
Speaker 17 (lower-pitched voice): chairman of the uh foreign relations committee also held hearings on iraq and with it had weapons of
Speaker 68 (lower-pitched voice): mass destruction which basically was
just
Speaker 68 (lower-pitched voice): a unceasing uh parade of kind of propaganda in
Speaker 17 (lower-pitched voice): favor of the war um he left out key voices you know scott ritter for example wasn't invited to that and scott wrote about it you know he said that this is basically just going to give cover for any war effort um and also the idea that he's been he's been saying
Speaker 23 (lower-pitched voice): that oh you know once the war was launched i
Speaker 17 (lower-pitched voice): realized how bad it was
Speaker 17 (lower-pitched voice): I immediately took it back and I opposed it, I realized it was a mistake. Not true, whatsoever.
I
Speaker 23 (lower-pitched voice): don't know how long this lasted, but suddenly until about maybe August or September of 2003, he was still very much in support of the war. He was saying that any democrat saying
Speaker 17 (lower-pitched voice): the opposite was wrong. He criticized Howard Dean on Fox News.
Speaker 17 (lower-pitched voice): Because how Dean was saying, you know, we have to pull out, yada, yada, yada. And Biden was saying, you
Speaker 6 (lower-pitched voice): know, no, no, that he does not speak for the Democratic Party. He was chastising any
Speaker 63: Democrat who at that point was suggesting a withdrawal and actually demanding that more troops be
Speaker 13 (lower-pitched voice): committed. Like his central criticism of the Bush administration at that point was that they weren't candid enough about how costly
–
the
Speaker 13 (lower-pitched voice): war would be in terms of not just money, but manpower. So he wanted the Bush administration
Speaker 111 (lower-pitched voice): to be more transparent in the amount of resources that needed to be allocated. Like, and he
Speaker 123: wanted more.
Speaker 104 (lower-pitched voice): Yeah. And yeah, and very much castigating liberals and Democrats, kind of paying them as kind of out of touch and unrealistic, which is a classic career long Biden move. To be fair to him, I will say that.
Speaker 104 (lower-pitched voice): Reportedly under Obama, he sounded like he was the only voice of reason in that administration. He opposed Libya and he opposed going to Syria and he opposed the bin Laden rate as well. I think he also,
Speaker 80 (lower-pitched voice): I think he opposed the Afghanistan surge in 09 as well.
Okay, well,
Speaker 124: there you go. Yeah, so you're right.
He
Speaker 13 (lower-pitched voice): was like, he was the...
Speaker 13 (lower-pitched voice): He was the foil to Hillary Clinton, who was in the opposite direction on all those issues. Yeah,
yeah,
Speaker 35: exactly. At the same time, you know, now he's been backing
Speaker 104 (lower-pitched voice): Guaido in Venezuela and saying that, you know, Maduro needs to be toppled there. And so, you know, it's...
Speaker 35: Yes. During the Obama administration, it sounds like he was not quite as hawkish as the rest of them. But the thing about him is that you just don't know. You really don't know. Particularly, Biden has this thing where throughout
Speaker 104 (lower-pitched voice): his career, he kind of
just
Speaker 104 (lower-pitched voice): gets swept up in any right-wing frenzy that kind of bubbles up, whether it's crime and drugs or the hysteria that engulfed U.S. culture after September 11 or the kind of very anti-government spending, anti-deficit stuff that happened in the Reagan and kind of basically continued on from there. He always kind of gets –
Speaker 104 (lower-pitched voice): Gets embroiled in these and any kind of his move is that he just takes it further than even the the right does To kind of prove that he is just as tough and you know, what have you serious, I guess And then so I mean I think for me the issue is if he became president How long is it before? something happens that that creates another You know right-wing friends, you know whether whether it's around invading Venezuela or God knows what
and
Speaker 104 (lower-pitched voice): And he succumbs
Speaker 103 (lower-pitched voice): to it because he's worried about the political fallout if he's seen to be not right-wing enough.
He's also
Speaker 125: borderline senile, so who knows what kind of influence can be exerted on him if he were actually in a position of power at this point.
Speaker 126: Yeah, which, I mean, even that, that's doubly scary. Yeah. I mean,
it
Speaker 10: could be that the Biden who had learned his lesson from Iraq was like the lucid Biden, you know. And then the one that we have now who's kind of still
–
Speaker 10: Seems to be you know living and in the time that he was a lifeguard at that swimming pool that Biden
Speaker 6 (lower-pitched voice): may not remember the Lessons of the Iraq war and some of these other wars that he supported, right?
So you
Speaker 111 (lower-pitched voice): and I have had exchanges about Tulsi Gabbard in the past I'm just curious if you followed
Speaker 13 (lower-pitched voice): her campaign a rhetoric much in the past couple months and if that
has
Speaker 13 (lower-pitched voice): altered your relatively pessimistic view about her. For example, I just watched a presentation that she made in New Hampshire two or three days ago, and she was talking about
Speaker 111 (lower-pitched voice): how somebody brought up nuclear weapons, and she was talking about how dangerous it is that the U.S. nuclear weapons
Speaker 108 (lower-pitched voice): stockpile is still on hair-trigger alert.
Speaker 108 (lower-pitched voice): which meaning that they could be launched in a
Speaker 20 (lower-pitched voice): matter of minutes. And she actually advocated that they be taken off hair trigger alert, which is not something that you hear much discussed, but is
Speaker 127 (lower-pitched voice): obviously like existentially important potentially. So it just seems to me like in
Speaker 88 (lower-pitched voice): following her pretty closely, she does cut against the grain and
Speaker 27 (lower-pitched voice): bring up issues that otherwise tend to get obscurity, even if you don't agree with
her, uh,
her
Speaker 71 (lower-pitched voice): approach uh a hundred percent so so has anything modified your your view on her i
think that uh a lot
Speaker 10: of stuff that she's brought
Speaker 23 (lower-pitched voice): to the table in this campaign has been good uh that's one example i think she was also one of the few maybe the only one um to comment on
Speaker 44 (lower-pitched voice): the julian assange
Speaker 17 (lower-pitched voice): uh arrest and basically say this is a bad thing uh bernie eventually did
Speaker 128: but she He was the most forceful in the earliest.
Speaker 10: Right, right. Yeah, and very, very quick off.
Speaker 10: the mark which is good the thing with with gabba is i i do not trust her and you know i'm very glad that she has taken
um
Speaker 23 (lower-pitched voice): she has moved to the left since 2016 um but she still basically says that she just wants to continue obama's foreign policy which is just
Speaker 17 (lower-pitched voice): uh do drone strikes and rely on special forces um that kind of thing uh you know i mean in the debate one of the debates
she
Speaker 17 (lower-pitched voice): When they were talking about the Iran deal, she kind of called it a flawed deal,
Speaker 44 (lower-pitched voice): which is – it's almost like she's signaling to the right because that's a common talking point among the right. This is a flawed
Speaker 31 (lower-pitched voice): deal. Hers is a little more nuanced. She did support the deal. She did
Speaker 130: support the deal.
Speaker 129: Well, she did eventually. I mean she – until she voted for it, she was –
Speaker 129: not into
Speaker 34: it. She was very critical of it. She actually
Speaker 17 (lower-pitched voice): voted to increase new sanctions on Iran once Rouhani was elected, which really undercut the prospect for peace. It happened ultimately, but
Speaker 17 (lower-pitched voice): This is not a thing that anyone on the left and even a lot of Democrats were happy about. Increasing
Speaker 34: sanctions on the run at that point was a very sensitive time. And she did eventually vote for it. That's true. But it came after a
Speaker 131: lot of stuff that was kind of in the opposite direction. And that deal, the vote for that deal did come after a lot of heavy lobbying
issues.
Speaker 44 (lower-pitched voice): from the Obama administration because this is viewed as one of the administration's great potential
Speaker 23 (lower-pitched voice): foreign policy accomplishments. So she kind of fell into line and she was very critical of the deal when she voted for it.
Speaker 65: So, I mean, you know, I'm not saying that's necessarily disqualifying, but – I think it's a
Speaker 132: little mush to say that she would
Speaker 94 (lower-pitched voice): just continue the Obama administration's foreign policy when –
Speaker 94 (lower-pitched voice): Her signature issue arguably was opposition to what she regarded as an ill-fated regime change initiative that the Obama administration
Speaker 13 (lower-pitched voice): waged in Syria. So that's a key difference between her outlook and that of the Obama administration
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): in Syria. I mean, Libya would be another example. You could go down the line. Yeah.
Speaker 88 (lower-pitched voice): Although it's true that she doesn't object on principle to every aspect of counterterrorism policy, but neither does Bernie, notwithstanding some of the rhetorical adjustments he made in that 2017 speech. I mean, I can remember the course of the 2016 campaign, and you actually mentioned this in one of your articles, where Bernie...
Speaker 88 (lower-pitched voice): said that he could imagine using drone strikes against terrorists and that there are threats that need to be combated, et cetera, et cetera. So I think just dismissing what she's
Speaker 20 (lower-pitched voice): advocating as a pure continuation of the Obama foreign policy is a little bit unsharitable.
Well, I
Speaker 10: mean, the Obama administration, the Libya debacle notwithstanding, which, by the way, what he did in Libya, he admitted that was a mistake, because that was pretty much against his instincts. Not that that means that much at the end, but I don't know if that was really, the Libya thing was really part of any sort of Obama doctrine. I think even he really regretted that. Let's leave that aside for a moment.
But I mean,
So
Speaker 10: accepting Libya, Obama's big
Speaker 23 (lower-pitched voice): thing was to increase the presence of drones and the reach of drones around the world and increase the way that
Speaker 10: they use to up the level of special forces, which, you know, even if you don't declare war, if you are sending special forces, which could be, you know, thousands of soldiers, you know, who
Speaker 17 (lower-pitched voice): don't maybe even more, that is still a war. And that is still...
Speaker 17 (lower-pitched voice): uh imperialism by any
Speaker 10: stretch a stretch of the imagination it's not a war that congress will vote on which in some ways makes it even um even and even more dangerous um and it's also a war that's going to be secret so there's very little public accountability and she hasn't said anything that i've seen perhaps i'm wrong but she hasn't said anything that that says that she's going to roll these things
Speaker 44 (lower-pitched voice): back
Speaker 134: um well i mean i i did i did an i did interview her for this very podcast and okay
Speaker 13 (lower-pitched voice): okay
Speaker 13 (lower-pitched voice): She was calling for a more circumspect – it's true that she doesn't object to it entirely on principle, right? But she was calling for a far
Speaker 20 (lower-pitched voice): more circumspect approach given the propensity for blowback, et cetera. So would I personally prefer a more full-throated rejection of the entirety of the counterterrorism enterprise sort of like on a more theoretical level? sure, but I don't think it's fair to say that she's
calling
Speaker 20 (lower-pitched voice): for it to be ramped up
Speaker 127 (lower-pitched voice): in the way that you suggest or at least that's not what she's been saying for the past since the campaign has been underway well
let me
Speaker 135: ask you this did you
Speaker 98: ask her if she still considers herself a hawk when it comes to terrorism because that's what she said in 2016
Speaker 134: right I mean we didn't get into that I mean maybe I ought to have I suppose but she did speak about that in her interview with
Glenn
Speaker 40 (lower-pitched voice): Greenwald and by the way I think it's
Speaker 13 (lower-pitched voice): notable this is a little bit of a side issue but she's the only candidate who's like
Doing
Speaker 13 (lower-pitched voice): interviews with people like Glenn Greenwald and myself. Not that we're the best, you know, not that we're like these shining examples of
Speaker 111 (lower-pitched voice): journalistic integrity or anything, but like, you know, she does a podcast with Matt Taibbi and she's like she actually has who I would regard to be positive influences
in
Speaker 40 (lower-pitched voice): so far as like doing that kind of media is suggestive of influence. So that gives
Speaker 88 (lower-pitched voice): me a little bit of a
of a.
Speaker 88 (lower-pitched voice): More of an appreciation for who at least
Speaker 13 (lower-pitched voice): she regards as like within her sphere, you know and
Speaker 63: That
Speaker 65: is encouraging.
Speaker 63: Yeah, and when she but when she
Speaker 111 (lower-pitched voice): Was asked about that with with Greenwald I mean the way I've always interpreted that comment is that She's
sort of
Speaker 111 (lower-pitched voice): inverting the typical notion of what a hawk means and
Speaker 111 (lower-pitched voice): Right. So the way that terrorism has been combated since 9-11 has had the consequence of actually
Speaker 13 (lower-pitched voice): inflaming terrorism in her mind and creating conditions whereby terrorism was more likely to come about, such as ISIS, Al Qaeda gaining more of a foothold in Syria and elsewhere. So.
She's
Speaker 13 (lower-pitched voice): actually saying that the
Speaker 88 (lower-pitched voice): quote-unquote hawkish way to combat terrorism is the opposite of what's been done in
terms of the
Speaker 92 (lower-pitched voice): predominant U.S. foreign policy
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): paradigm, and she focuses on regime change principally, but the reason being, she feels
Speaker 88 (lower-pitched voice): as though that has fueled and fostered terrorism, and actually, if you truly want to combat it, you have to change just the basic premises that underlie terrorism.
US
Speaker 88 (lower-pitched voice): foreign policy. I mean, for example, she's she gave an interview with NPR in July, I believe, and she was asked, do you
Speaker 40 (lower-pitched voice): think that any what US foreign policy or what US interventions do you think have been legitimate since in recent history? And she cited she said none since World War Two. Like, so
Speaker 13 (lower-pitched voice): none of no US intervention since World War Two in her mind had
been.
Speaker 13 (lower-pitched voice): legitimate i'm paraphrasing um but i think it i think it's wrong i think it's wrong to dismiss
Speaker 40 (lower-pitched voice): a candidate
who would say
Speaker 40 (lower-pitched voice): something as relatively extreme in a positive way i would say as that as somebody who's just sort of like conventional
Speaker 136: and just wants to continue what the the liberal
Speaker 137 (lower-pitched voice): consensus was pre-trump you know well i mean that
is
Speaker 131: the liberal consensus i mean obama would describe himself the same way he'd say i don't want to do more regime change i think it's the wrong thing to go in and try and topple a
Speaker 10: dictator obviously he did that during libya
Speaker 10: But again, he came to regret that. And he actually, he shied away from his threat when he was going to strike Syria. Obviously, the Syria policy is bigger than just that one act. But still, I mean, Obama would say that he's actually doing the more responsible thing by using what he calls surgical strikes, quote unquote,
Speaker 23 (lower-pitched voice): which, by the way, is the same thing Gabbard says. And by using special forces to just sort of kind of, you know, surgically strike and strike a
Speaker 131: very specific particular path.
Speaker 131: Are we
Speaker 138: saying that Bernie has ruled out surgical strikes at this point?
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): No, I haven't. But, well, for example, Sanders has voted against all of Trump's military budgets. Gabard hasn't. Sanders hasn't done some of those anti-Iran votes that Gabard did in the lead up to the Iran deal, for example. You know, the other thing that we're not talking about as well is the very, very weird situation.
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): the connections Gabart has with Hindu nationalists, which I don't know why this should not be something that is off limits to talk about if a candidate had extensive links with the far right overseas organization that Gabart has with the RSS and the BJP.
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): that would be a really huge deal and you know it's significant the fact that she said you know one of the things that the US has to ally with India over one of the one of the common pieces of common ground that they can work together on is fighting terrorism now look
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): Maybe Sanders, if he even wins, he gets in and all this stuff about we have to change course from just sort of bombing and thinking that just bombing and killing people is going
Speaker 131: to change things and end terrorism, maybe he dispenses with all that. But
he has
Speaker 131: at least acknowledged that that's the case. I don't know if Gabbard has really acknowledged that, yes, regime change, very bad.
Speaker 131: We know that's
Speaker 139: definitely going to exacerbate and make things even worse than if it was just
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): the counterterrorism plus, quote
Speaker 140: unquote, option or strategy that Obama took. But the thing is,
Speaker 141: drone strikes and special
Speaker 131: forces strikes still kill people. They still make people resentful towards the U.S. government.
Speaker 131: They still make people terrified
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): to
be in
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): their homes. I mean, what was one of the first things that Trump did when he became president? He launched that raid in Yemen where, what was it, like 30 people died,
Speaker 131: mostly civilians, a little girl. You know, drone strikes, it's really
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): worth acknowledging how destructive and psychologically damaging drone strikes are. They're very often...
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): Well, one, we don't actually know for sure how many militants they're killing because Obama, of course, put it so that any military-age male that is killed by a drone counts as a militant. And it's all very untransparent. It's very hard to get information. We have sort of – there are organizations on the ground that can't keep track of this stuff, but the government doesn't, and it has very misleading statistics that puts us – misleading and flawed.
Speaker 131: But people are dying A lot of people are dying And even if they don't die Imagine the terror of going about your life
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): And knowing that if you hear that noise That distinctive noise of a drone flying That this could
be
Speaker 131: the end People were killed at weddings The happiest day of their lives They and
Speaker 141: everyone they knew Was slaughtered in
just
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): the space of A few minutes, maybe half an hour
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): Um, that is, if, if we, if that keeps
Speaker 131: happening, it's, it's not going to matter if you don't do regime change because terrorists are going to keep
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): springing up. Um, because you know, there's, there's still this far off power that is just launching, um, death from the sky, uh, at you and your family for no particular reason. Um, and that's going to keep creating terrorists. It's going to keep creating people who want to hurt Americans. And again, whether Sanders follows
Speaker 5 (lower-pitched voice): up in his speech or not, that remains to be seen. But he at least acknowledges that that is not the case, that that would not work. And I don't know if Gabard has. I think
Speaker 41 (lower-pitched voice): she has acknowledged that in certain respects, probably
Speaker 8 (lower-pitched voice): not in the wholesale way that Bernie did. And I agree with you in terms of the terror wrought by drone strikes, so no disagreement on the substance
Speaker 27 (lower-pitched voice): there. It's more about what she has said to acknowledge that
Speaker 27 (lower-pitched voice): What you just laid out there, I think, I think it's a little more extensive than perhaps you appreciate.
And
Speaker 142: then also on the issue
Speaker 65: of what has she said about drone strikes and special because to me, OK,
Speaker 10: look, I totally understand the support for her as kind of the anti imperialist candidate as a candidate is kind of willing to go further
Speaker 23 (lower-pitched voice): than anyone in terms of challenging these kind of basic precepts of US foreign policy. I totally get that.
Speaker 23 (lower-pitched voice): But
Speaker 65: she's not, she's not willing to go as far as she could. I mean, if she wanted to make this really the issue and someone who's completely different from the rest of the field, why, and even different from someone like Sanders, then why not say we need to move away from this aspect as well and be better than Sanders on it? And the fact that she won't, I mean, I can't call her an
Speaker 23 (lower-pitched voice): anti-imperialist.
If
Speaker 23 (lower-pitched voice): she's still very much focused on eradicating terrorism through
Speaker 143: just kind of bombing random villages in the Middle East No,
Speaker 144: that's fair. I mean, I think it's it's more a matter of emphasis free for her
Speaker 111 (lower-pitched voice): You're right that she overwhelmingly emphasizes the regime change aspect which even if it's
Speaker 111 (lower-pitched voice): Sort of conventional wisdom now
Speaker 13 (lower-pitched voice): or approaching conventional wisdom in the Democratic Party to be at least in theory against regime change. The
way that she
Speaker 13 (lower-pitched voice): discusses it, I think is a little
Speaker 41 (lower-pitched voice): it's a it's more it's more comprehensive and it's more rooted in a philosophical niche that she's she's
Speaker 108 (lower-pitched voice): carved out. And I just don't think
like.
Maybe I
Speaker 108 (lower-pitched voice): could ask her more about it. Right. But I don't know that have any of the candidates really been asked about drone strikes recently. I just don't know that it's enough of a hot topic where they're being held accountable
Speaker 20 (lower-pitched voice): for what their views are. It's just like it's so it's a matter of like what gets brought up that she
hasn't.
Speaker 20 (lower-pitched voice): disgusted it
Speaker 10: I agree but this is her issue I mean this is this is like uh like Santa's you know
whose
Speaker 145: whose big issue is kind of inequality and the uh the the domination of the country by wealthy interests not being asked
Speaker 10: a
Speaker 61 (lower-pitched voice): very basic
Speaker 10: question about you know um about that that subject so I mean
I I
Speaker 10: think that she does have to answer and listen I would love to be proven
wrong
I
Speaker 10: would very much love it. It would be great to have someone
Speaker 17 (lower-pitched voice): who is a consistent and far more radical voice against the direction of U.S. foreign policy for the last, you know, at least 20 years, you know, ideally
Speaker 10: more. So that would be great. I'm not I'm not sold yet that Gabart is that person.
Speaker 10: But, you know, it may well be that in the in the coming years, because,
Speaker 17 (lower-pitched voice): you know, I assume she'll be in the in the political scene for a while. It may well be that we that she kind of maintains this position. And if after, you know, four years, maybe
Speaker 23 (lower-pitched voice): more.
um
Speaker 23 (lower-pitched voice): i see that she really has you know committed to this and and and and really has reoriented the way she thought about it um i'll be very willing to say you know i in the same way that i that i have in about sanders i'll be very willing to say you know um i i think she has moved and and that's good and and we should really have
Speaker 17 (lower-pitched voice): another closer look
at it
Speaker 146: that's fair and uh just just very briefly because you mentioned the modi thing
i think
I don't
Speaker 146: want to
Speaker 13 (lower-pitched voice): sound like an apologist, right? I know that's going to be the inevitable accusation. But I do think that the links and the ties that people assert between her and the RSS
Speaker 41 (lower-pitched voice): and such have been a little bit overstated. I don't want to dwell on that because I want to wrap up soon because we've been going for a while. So one final
Speaker 147: question.
Speaker 148: Well, can I just say –
Speaker 148: On
Speaker 149: that topic, there was a piece written for The Caravan, which is an album I'm not familiar with. Very exhaustive. I mean, it took me like over an hour to read. But I mean, I think it's pretty significant.
I
Speaker 10: mean, you know, whether it was an RSS person or a BJP person, I can't remember. But there was somebody
Speaker 35: from one of those entities that was at her wedding.
Speaker 35: Which, yeah, again, you
Speaker 25: know, if we were talking about a far-right party
Speaker 150: from Europe that was like at some
Speaker 10: politician's wedding, we would be pretty alarmed. And that's just one kind of drop in the
ocean of all
Speaker 10: these different countries.
Speaker 64 (lower-pitched voice): Right, but the context there, right, and I said I wasn't going to dwell on it, but I guess I'll dwell on it momentarily. I mean, the context there was that.
She
Speaker 41 (lower-pitched voice): was the first Hindu ever elected to the U.S. Congress, right? So in that capacity,
Speaker 13 (lower-pitched voice): she was the head of the kind of U.S.-Indian Relations Caucus. She obviously wanted to forge ties with
Speaker 94 (lower-pitched voice): what was then the ruling party in India at the time of her wedding, right? That's her diplomatic approach. She wants to forge ties with everybody, which
Speaker 20 (lower-pitched voice): you can agree or disagree with.
Speaker 20 (lower-pitched voice): And so, obviously, her being a Hindu attracted a certain amount of interest and intrigue amongst
Speaker 41 (lower-pitched voice): especially the American Indian diaspora, most of whom, by the way, are Democrats, who have given to other
Speaker 71 (lower-pitched voice): democratic Hindu candidates in terms of financial contributions. So,
Speaker 63: you know, I feel as though...
But
Speaker 13 (lower-pitched voice): the ideological implication in the notion that she had this direct somehow political affinity with those people by dint of those quote-unquote ties seems
Speaker 94 (lower-pitched voice): to me a little overstated, and I did read that long.
Speaker 43: Well, people should read that piece and make up their minds, but would we say the same thing about Israel? People
Speaker 23 (lower-pitched voice): can and do say similar justifications. We have to maintain ties with an important ally.
Speaker 23 (lower-pitched voice): they'll say you know because of religious elements i'm uh this this is why i have all these links to kind of far
Speaker 17 (lower-pitched voice): right uh israeli figures or something um i mean i think
i
Speaker 94 (lower-pitched voice): think i think the centrality of israel in terms of u.s foreign policy makes it more of a unique case
Speaker 71 (lower-pitched voice): than than india um in terms of why that would be troubling if you could ascertain those quote-unquote ties
um
But
Speaker 152: anyway, yeah, people could read it for themselves. Yeah,
Speaker 107 (lower-pitched voice): yeah, I think, yeah, we probably won't end up agreeing on this, but people should read
Speaker 124: it, and they may not agree with me, they may well agree with you, but yeah, The Caravan is the publication.
Speaker 36: Right.
Okay,
Speaker 111 (lower-pitched voice): so final question here. Now that we're in the midst of this Ukraine gate
Speaker 153: flare-up,
what do
Speaker 154: you think that
Speaker 111 (lower-pitched voice): portends in terms of foreign policy? Because one thing that drives me nuts about it
Speaker 111 (lower-pitched voice): Is that the core allegation,
Speaker 88 (lower-pitched voice): right, is supposedly that Trump used U.S. military aid to Ukraine as a point of leverage to extract a commitment from Zelensky to
Speaker 108 (lower-pitched voice): investigate whether it was Biden or
whether it
Speaker 108 (lower-pitched voice): was the origins of the Russia investigation is sort of like muddled. But in any event, he was
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): he wanted.
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): the allegations that he was using military aid as an instrument of obtaining political benefit for himself. And everybody
Speaker 94 (lower-pitched voice): seems to forget that the question of whether it's wise or sound policy to send military aid in the first place is like something that's still
Speaker 13 (lower-pitched voice): like a live issue that probably warrants a little bit of consideration. Like
they
Speaker 155: got totally drowned
Speaker 13 (lower-pitched voice): out in the midst of
Speaker 21 (lower-pitched voice): the partisan Fuhrer.
Speaker 21 (lower-pitched voice): And that aspect to me has just been maddening.
Yeah, you
Speaker 43: know, this issue is just, it's so tiresome and just dull
Speaker 104 (lower-pitched voice): in many ways. Not because it's not necessarily that there's interesting things to it, but it's just the rhetoric, the discourse around it is so...
Speaker 104 (lower-pitched voice): divorced from reality and unhinged and and just uh in some well actually in many cases just flat out wrong um that it's it's yeah i
Speaker 156: i've honestly kind of disengaged from it i i've kept up with it a little bit my my thoughts on it are this
first of all
Speaker 131: it's not clear to me i've seen multiple people claim different
Speaker 104 (lower-pitched voice): things because i thought the issue was that he had used the military aid and kind of it was hinting that he would condition
it um
Speaker 104 (lower-pitched voice): on basically the Ukrainian president, the new Ukrainian president finding, or perhaps just making something out of thin air about Biden and the
Speaker 17 (lower-pitched voice): Burisma controversy. But then
Speaker 104 (lower-pitched voice): there's other people who are saying that the problem with the kind of impeachable offense, the great crime involved, is that he tried to get another country to involve itself in the U.S. political
Speaker 131: process.
Speaker 131: Um, which is if that, if that's what people think the crime is, then of course the question is, well, why, why was
it
Speaker 156: okay for Hillary Clinton to, uh, work with Ukraine to get dead on Trump? It's literally the exact same thing. Um,
but
Speaker 59: people just pretend like that either didn't happen or they just pretend that it's a conspiracy theory, which is absolutely not Politico reported on it. Right. Um, or they,
Speaker 40 (lower-pitched voice): or they pretend that it's a right wing talking point or something. Right. In addition to bringing up the Steele dossier, remember that?
Speaker 40 (lower-pitched voice): which was the epitome of using political power in the case of Hillary Clinton in the DNC, although she wasn't obviously president. She did use her stature indirectly, so she did it with a little bit of
Speaker 111 (lower-pitched voice): at least initial plausible deniability to...
Speaker 111 (lower-pitched voice): Make a case against Trump that was based on, quote unquote, foreign assistance that they contracted with a spy to compile. So, like, what is the operating principle here that we're supposed to believe is automatically leads to impeachment? Right. What is so unique about this that
Speaker 88 (lower-pitched voice): you couldn't also make the same allegation of
Trump?
Speaker 88 (lower-pitched voice): other parties and other
Speaker 92 (lower-pitched voice): figures for that is what I'm struggling to comprehend still.
Speaker 43: Well, and the answer is it doesn't seem like there is. I mean, you know, again if it's about conditioning military aid then okay,
but
Speaker 104 (lower-pitched voice): it seems like a lot of people are saying that the military aid is kind of beside the point. It's just a fact that any country was being invited to you know, engage itself in the US political process
and I
Speaker 104 (lower-pitched voice): mean, that's ridiculous as well. I mean Mitt Romney um
has
Speaker 104 (lower-pitched voice): obviously made headlines by condemning Trump over this. But
Speaker 158: Mitt Romney and Netanyahu during the 2012 election were basically working in cahoots to get Obama.
Speaker 159: Netanyahu cut TV ads, I believe, for Mitt Romney, if I'm remembering correctly. Yeah, no,
Speaker 156: I believe that is correct. So it's like...
Speaker 156: Again, I mean it's basically
Speaker 104 (lower-pitched voice): just – the principle seems to be if – it's bad if the consensus of the kind of political
Speaker 38: establishment or national security establishment says it's bad.
Speaker 61 (lower-pitched voice): Oh, it's fine for Israel to constantly involve itself in U.S. affairs in outrageous ways that no country would be normally able to do, but
Speaker 35: that's because they're an ally.
And
Speaker 35: of course, as you said, with Ukraine, Ukraine's an ally, but there's been no discussion about whether it's
Speaker 104 (lower-pitched voice): wise or morally right to be arming or at the least giving aid to an ally that has the significant presence of neo-Nazis and other far-right elements in the state.
I
Speaker 104 (lower-pitched voice): mean, that seems like it's kind of – if we oppose Trump because he's supposedly a fascist or what have you, white supremacist, maybe that deserves to have some discussion as well. But of course, no, because again, I
Speaker 107 (lower-pitched voice): think you probably agree with me here.
I
Speaker 104 (lower-pitched voice): don't think this has anything to do with principle. I think it's the Democrats just wanting to get Trump out. And of course, who wouldn't want to get Trump out for multiple reasons? Yeah.
Speaker 160: But the way that
Speaker 125: you go about doing it also matters because of the
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): potential disadvantageous principles that the process could
Speaker 8 (lower-pitched voice): enshrine if it's done in a way that is totally unmoored
Speaker 13 (lower-pitched voice): from
any...
Speaker 13 (lower-pitched voice): Any recognition of reality in the sense that you actually want to at least pretend that you're advancing a coherent principle if you're saying that the president should be impeached over it. And if it just falls apart upon minimal examination, people are going to conclude that it's just this knee jerk partisan thing, which is going to inflame tensions
for all
Speaker 13 (lower-pitched voice): the wrong
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): reasons and give proponents of Trump perhaps even a legitimate grievance.
To
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): question
Speaker 92 (lower-pitched voice): why it is he's being undercut in this manner rather than just letting it go forward with the electoral cycle when, you know, Trump isn't to the extent that it's noxious elements can be repudiated at the ballot box that that can that can take place. So they're they're they're preempting that with this sort of march toward.
I'm not
Speaker 92 (lower-pitched voice): going to say extra legal removal, because obviously impeachment is in the Constitution, but it would be so unprecedented for it to happen. Literally, it has never happened that the
Speaker 108 (lower-pitched voice): president has been removed, although they too have been impeached. But were it to happen, you could just imagine it creating such hysteria
that I think
Speaker 137 (lower-pitched voice): it's it's almost unfathomable that I would actually produce anything that's politically beneficial.
Speaker 161: But then again, who knows?
Speaker 43: Right. Well, and the other thing is that this if this fails, you can't impeach Trump ever
Speaker 107 (lower-pitched voice): again, because now the first time they did it was something that turned out to be completely untrue.
Now, I
Speaker 107 (lower-pitched voice): mean, you know, this obviously is true. But if it turns out that you mean, if it turns out, I mean, they first like
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): if they first at least attempted to initiate the process around Mueller and that right was ill-fated.
Right.
Speaker 163: yeah to say the least um and the thing is i mean
Speaker 104 (lower-pitched voice): it's you know it seems based on reporting i know bloomberg has said that it's just the claim that that uh there was an investigation to burisma and biden's son when he had the prosecutor fired was completely wrong um but let's say that it does turn out to be true because it could be if i'm wrong biden hasn't like actually explicitly denied um
Speaker 104 (lower-pitched voice): That doesn't happen. I think he said, you know, there's no
Speaker 10: credible outlet that gives a credence. That doesn't mean that actually happened. But I don't know. It's a little when you when you just say
Speaker 156: outright, this is completely untrue. Perhaps perhaps that's nothing. But
Speaker 164: let's say that I mean, he's denied all wrongdoing,
Speaker 40 (lower-pitched voice): which allows him to evade getting into the specifics.
Yeah,
Speaker 10: right. And again, it also depends on how Trump phrased the request, which I'm not off the top of my head. I'm 100% sure how he did it. But let's say that in the course of this impeachment, they find out that, because I think they're actually going to do an investigation again in Ukraine as well. Let's say that they find, maybe if Biden didn't do that, but that there was really
Speaker 31 (lower-pitched voice): some serious
investigation.
Speaker 31 (lower-pitched voice): you know uh shady stuff going on between you know what his son was doing
Speaker 35: and and his position as vice president well that essentially vindicates trump um i mean you know maybe
the
Speaker 10: democrats have to hope that that is not the case because if it is that completely undercuts the entire thing they're saying because it makes trump look like the hero like oh no he was actually doing the right thing he
was he was uh
Speaker 10: using military aid in order to to crack down on corruption
and
Speaker 35: We'll see. If you're Joe Biden, you're going to be sweating right now because this
is
Speaker 104 (lower-pitched voice): going to just lay out for the public just how dirty and corrupt the Democratic Party is. Maybe not as bad as the
Speaker 35: Republican Party, but pretty bad. That's not great going into an election.
What do you
Speaker 80 (lower-pitched voice): think this does to just the wider political climate? Because this is sort
of a
Speaker 80 (lower-pitched voice): theory that I've been advancing, which is that when
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): everything gets distilled into this binary choice of impeachment versus no impeachment, it kind of constricts the range of acceptable political discussion into this pretty tiny box. And I struggle to see
Speaker 13 (lower-pitched voice): how that benefits people.
For
Speaker 40 (lower-pitched voice): example, Bernie, who obviously is trying to expand the paradigm politically for what's available
Speaker 13 (lower-pitched voice): to people. It just seems as though if everybody's laser-focused on impeachment for the next four or five months or something,
again, it's
Speaker 13 (lower-pitched voice): difficult to predict, but I have a hard time imagining how that benefits
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): him. It's not as though, you know,
the...
The
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): procedural minutiae that's attendant to impeachment, such as, you know, what articles are going to be referred to what committee and what witnesses are going to be called, et
Speaker 88 (lower-pitched voice): cetera, et cetera, like what statutes were violated. That's not really in his political wheelhouse. So I sort of question whether whether a political climate dominated
Speaker 92 (lower-pitched voice): by this is conducive in particular to.
to
Speaker 92 (lower-pitched voice): his interests. I mean, but obviously, who can say
Speaker 165: but that's just my sense.
Speaker 166: Yeah, well, I haven't seen the polling about this.
Speaker 10: If it's anything like I mean, I know that there are people
Speaker 23 (lower-pitched voice): who are the majority for the favor impeachment. But as far as the polling of, you know, where people rank this and the and the issues that are most important to them. I mean, I would assume that's probably similar to Russia gay, which was kind
Speaker 10: of near zero for most voters, you know, so I think,
I think,
You
Speaker 10: know, he and the rest of the candidates will have to kind
of like
Speaker 23 (lower-pitched voice): genuflect of this and kind of like, oh, yeah, yeah, this is important. But, you know, let's get back to the real meat and potatoes issues. I think they realize that they're not going to actually, at least when it comes to running a campaign, they're
Speaker 113: not going to beat Trump by focusing on this, even though they have to basically say they support it. Well, I mean,
Speaker 167: Warren is happy to focus on it to some extent anyway. I mean, I went to her big
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): speech in New York City a couple weeks ago.
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): and she made one of her
Speaker 88 (lower-pitched voice): signature rallying cries, we must impeach Trump. So like it's something that she does bring up on her own accord, 'cause she obviously perceived there to be some political benefit in her talking about it a lot.
Speaker 169: - Right, well,
Speaker 170: I didn't know that. - Yeah. - Yeah, I mean maybe-- - It's like part of her stump
speech.
I'm
Speaker 112: sure
Speaker 10: it ties into her drive for anti-corruption, because this is an example of corruption. The problem there, though, is the Hunter Biden thing is also an example of corruption. When Warren was asked about that, when asked, would your vice president, would their child be able to sit on the board of a foreign company?
Speaker 10: She she said
Speaker 23 (lower-pitched voice): yes. And then and then instantly said, actually, I'm not sure I have to I have to check. So if she's going to make this a centerpiece of her campaign, I think she has to be ready to say that what Biden did was wrong as well. And that's sort of the issue that when you actually make this a center point of your kind of candidacy, you run into these issues because she's going to I mean, you don't want to you don't want to be stuck on stage having to defend what Biden did or like waving it away.
Speaker 23 (lower-pitched voice): Particularly if you're someone like someone like Elizabeth Warren whose entire thing is about good government and Ethics and and rooting out the influence of money I mean the other
Speaker 113: thing is I What do people think is going to happen when they impeach him? I mean, you know, I think Trump deserves to be impeached for all manner of heinous crimes that are far worse than this
Ukraine thing and
But
Speaker 113: what do people think is going to happen? I mean, even if you get rid of him...
They
Speaker 171: haven't thought that deeply about it.
Speaker 112: Right. I mean, Mike Pence would possibly even be more dangerous than Trump. I mean, the one thing we know about Trump is that he's at least inconsistently
Speaker 17 (lower-pitched voice): committed to...
Speaker 17 (lower-pitched voice): to to uh kind of avoiding war you know he he has
Speaker 10: at times again very inconsistently very inconsistently but he has at times pushed back against some of the some of the war stuff he
Speaker 61 (lower-pitched voice): caught off that iranian uh strike at the last minute uh because apparently tucker carlson called him um i don't
Speaker 96 (lower-pitched voice): think mike pence would do that i don't think mike pence is going to get a call from tucker carlson and then change his mind um at the last minute there was
Speaker 13 (lower-pitched voice): reporting actually recently about that Iran incident that said, you know, Pence was shocked
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): and
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): and dismayed when Trump called off the strikes of the last-- - Oh,
Speaker 10: good. Great.
Well, there
Speaker 10: you go. I think that's a thing that no one ever really talks about. I mean, I guess everyone assumes that it's not gonna work, but I don't know, I mean, if you're really committed to this as a serious policy, shouldn't you discuss what the
Speaker 23 (lower-pitched voice): post-Trump strategy is? I don't know.
- I don't
Speaker 172: know, it's a mess. That's all I know.
Speaker 173: yeah all right so uh
Speaker 94 (lower-pitched voice): why don't we leave it there thank you for
Speaker 27 (lower-pitched voice): having a protracted discussion it was uh interesting i hope quite all
right
Speaker 174: yeah it was uh it was enjoyable all
right maybe we'll
Speaker 174: do it again sometime yeah for sure take
Speaker 175: care all right take
it okay there you
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): have it
As
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): always, if you found this edifying, please consider a contribution through Patreon or PayPal, the information for which is in the description box.
So I will
Speaker 1 (lower-pitched voice): see you next time. Fare thee well.